Guide to the Marjorie L. Shuer Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Marjorie L. Shuer papers
1966-1997
SC0733
Shuer, Marjorie L.
0.75 Linear feet
These papers largely reflect Shuer's interest in women's sports and include correspondence, clippings, articles, reports, notes, and assorted records from several Stanford University athletic committees and from its Department of Athletics, Physical Education and Recreation. The clippings primarily date from the 1970s, with some from the 1990s. The correspondence includes incoming and outgoing letters; subjects include her participation in Stanford athletic committees, her own career, and the effort to get recognition for Stanford women athletes. Also of note in the papers are materials from a questionnaire distributed to female athletes at Stanford in 1971.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Marjorie L. Shuer M.D. earned her AB in 1972 in psychology at Stanford; as an undergraduate she was a member of the women's swimming, track and field, and sailing teams. She received an M.A. in exercise physiology from the University of Michigan and her M.D. for the University of Texas School of Medicine. In her career she has been Assistant Clinical Professor, Department of Psychiatry, UCSD, chief psychiatrist at San Diego County's Juvenile Hall, and the Lead Medical Officer for Slalom Kayak and the Flat Water Canoe and Kayak at the 1996 Olympic Games in Atlanta.
Description of the Collection
These papers largely reflect Shuer's interest in women's sports and include correspondence, clippings, articles, reports, notes, and assorted records from several Stanford University athletic committees and from its Department of Athletics, Physical Education and Recreation. The clippings primarily date from the 1970s, with some from the 1990s. The correspondence includes incoming and outgoing letters; subjects include her participation in Stanford athletic committees, her own career, and the effort to get recognition for Stanford women athletes. Also of note in the papers are materials from a questionnaire distributed to female athletes at Stanford in 1971.
Access Terms
Shuer, Marjorie L.; Stanford University. Department of Athletics, Physical Education and Recreation.; Stanford University. Department of Athletics.; Sex discrimination in sports.; Sports for women.
Collection Contents
- Papers
  - Article (photocopy of typescript) on Margie Shuer, ca. 1975 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Articles by Shuer 1974, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Athletic questionnaire (Stanford), 1971 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Bem, Sandra, "Training the Woman to Know her Place: the Power of a Nonconscious Ideology," 1971 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Class materials, Human Biology (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Clippings on women's college sports (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Clippings on women's college sports (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Clippings on women's college sports [original newsprint] (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1966-97 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence miscellaneous [not to or from Shuer], 1978, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - A Guide for Stanford Women, ca. 1972 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Impact of events scale (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Indiana University swim team (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Miscellaneous notes (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Paper on women and athletics, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Personal papers: copies of USOC certification and CA teacher's credential (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Schleihauf, Bob, "Swimming Propulsion: A Hydrodynamic Analysis" (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - School papers by Shuer, 1971 and n.d. (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Sports medicine (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Typescript reports, articles, notes, primarily on women's sports, some specific to Stanford University (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Stanford University Administrative Panel on Internal Athletic, Physical Education and Recreational Programs, records, 1971-72 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Stanford University Committee on Athletics, Physical Education and Recreation (CAPER), minutes and agenda, 1970-72 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Stanford University CAPER, reports and memos, 1971-72 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Stanford University Dept. of Athletics, Physical Education and Recreation, assorted memos, reports, and other records, 1970-75 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Stanford University Dept. of Athletics, Physical Education and Recreation, assorted memos etc., 1970-77 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Washington State document re Title IX 1976 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Women, sports and the law – notes (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Women's Equity Action League Newsletter, March 1974 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - "SU 69", 2 film reel(s) (8mm) (Box 2, Folder 6)